Finding Aid for G. B. Harrison Papers 1910-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
G. B. Harrison Papers 1910-1981
Harrison, G. B. (George Bagshawe), 1894-
18 microfilm rolls
7 linear feet
Scholar and professor of English at University of Michigan. Diaries, manuscripts of dramas and other writings, Shakespearean notes and lecture materials and personal and professional correspondence, including correspondence and other material relating to his service with the British Infantry during World War I.
851423; Aa/2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by G.B. Harrison (donor no. 4851 ) in 1971 and 1973. Additional files were received in 1985.
The collection is open for research.
Professor George Bagshawe Harrison was born in Hove, Sussex, England, on July 14, 1894. His education at Queens' College, Cambridge, was interrupted by the first world war, during which he served in India and Mesopotamia. In 1919 he returned to Cambridge, where he took a first class degree in English literature in 1920, one of the first such awarded.
Harrison became reader in English literature at King's College, London, in 1924, and remained there until the start of the second world war, when he rejoined the army. In 1943 he was released from the army to take up the post of Head of the Department of English at Queen's University, Ontario. In 1949 he went to the University of Michigan, and in 1963-64 he was a member of the English faculty at the University of Windsor, in Windsor, Ontario. His publications include, besides his editions of the plays, a guide, the Companion to Shakespeare Studies (with Harley Granville-Barker), books on John Bunyan and the Earl of Essex, and the remarkable fictional Elizabethan and Jacobean journals. After his retirement, Harrison served on the International Commission on English in the Liturgy, for the Roman Catholic Church, for which he was instrumental in translating the Latin Mass into English.
Professor Harrison, Shakespeare scholar, editor, and teacher, died in New Zealand on November 1, 1991, at the age of 97. Professor Harrison not only taught many hundreds of students of English literature during his forty years of service at universities in Britain, Canada, and the United States, but he was known to tens of thousands more from his text of Shakespeare's Complete Works, widely used in university courses since its publication in 1952.
In 1985, Harrison published his memoirs One man in his time; the memoirs of G.B. Harrison 1894-1984 (The Dunmore Press Ltd)
The collection contain diaries, personal and professional correspondence, articles, lectures, research notes, and literary manuscripts; material relates extensively to Shakespearean, Elizabethan, and Jacobean literary scholarship and the teaching thereof, to Catholicism (including the English liturgy), and to Harrison's service with the British Infantry in India and Mesopotamia (Iraq) during World War I. There is also material relating to feminism, publishing and copyright, rare books, and staging Elizabethan plays. Noteworthy is the extensive and substantive correspondence with Guy Hamilton and Gerald Cullinan, which ranges over literature, scholarship, politics, and personalities in the U.S. and England.
The G.B. Harrison collection is divided into the following series: Diaries; Correspondence; Religious Activities; Addresses and Lectures; Articles, Reviews, and Pamphlets; and Manuscripts of writings.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan.; Catholic Church.; Harrison, G. B. (George Bagshawe), 1894-1991; India.; Iraq.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1914-1918.
Contributors:
Cullinan, Gerald.; Hamilton, Guy.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.
- Diaries
  - April 1910 (Italy) (Box 1)
  - World War I (India and Mesopotamia) 1914-1918, 6 volumes (in 3 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - September 1943-May 1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1974, 25 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1975-1981, 7 volumes (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  - General
    - Letter-press books
      - October 1926-July 1927, 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - July 1927-July 1928, 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - July 1928-October 1929, 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - July 1929-April 1930, 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - April 1930-Whitsunday 1935, 5 volumes (Box 3)
    - Recordings by GBH of some of the correspondence from his letter-press books, 7 reels
      (prior to the receipt of the originals, GBH made oral recordings of some of his correspondence from the letter-press books which he considered otherwise illegible; transcriptions were never made of these recordings)
      - re publication of Companion to Shakespeare studies, 1932-1933, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    - World War I (letters to parents from India and Mesopotamia) December 1914-September 1916, March 1918 (Box 4)
    - 1930s (Box 4)
    - 1940s (Box 4)
    - 1944-1949 (Box 4)
      re leaving Queens University and arriving at University of Michigan; includes resume
    - 1950s (Box 4)
    - 1960s (Box 4)
    - 1970s-1980 (Box 4)
    - Fragments and undated (Box 4)
  - Special Correspondents
    - Guy Hamilton
      - 1926 (from GBH only) (Box 4)
      - 1927 (from GBH only) (Box 4)
      - 1929 (from GBH only) (Box 4)
      - 1928-1948 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - Gerald Cullinan
      - 1965-1967 (Box 4)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 4)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - 1974-1976 (Box 4)
      - 1977-1980 (Box 4)
    - "The Tulsa Feminists," re Profession of English 1974 (Box 4)
    - Hyman Enzer (Professor of Sociology, Hofstra University), re GBH's first published novel Fires of Arcadia, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
  - Shakespeare and Other Writings
    - re Companion to Shakespeare 1932 (Box 4)
    - re Copy of Holinshed's Chronicles though to belong to Shakespeare 1935 (Box 4)
    - With agent and publisher re Introducing Shakespeare, College Shakespeare, and Complete Shakespeare, 1942-1952 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - Re problems with citations in New Readers' Shakespeare, 1945 (Box 4)
    - With Martin Holmes re illustrations for Harcourt Brace edition of Shakespeare 1946 (Box 4)
    - With George A. Harrap and Co., Ltd. re Tyrone Guthrie's introduction to GBH work 1952-1953 (Box 5)
    - With Arthur Eastman re collaboration on Shakespeare's Critics, 1962 (Box 5)
    - With publisher re Adventures in English Literature and Major British Writers 1963-1965 (Box 5)
    - Re GBH's reviews of books by A.L. Rowse 1963-1965 (Box 5)
    - Re Proposed project for Cliff's Notes 1966-1967 (Box 5)
- Religious Activities
  - Conversion to Catholicism 1946 (includes correspondence and a memoir) (Box 5)
  - International Commission on English in the Liturgy (ICLE) 1966-1978 (includes correspondence, diary entries, and meditations) (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets and Radio Addresses 1976-1982 (include correspondence and texts) (Box 5)
- Addresses and Lectures
  - On Shakespeare, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - On Catholicism and Religion, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, especially Elizabethan literature (Box 5)
    folders 1-2
  - Miscellaneous, especially Elizabethan literature (Box 6)
    folders 3-7
- Articles, Reviews, and Pamphlets (including scattered reviews of GBH's work)
  - Scrapbooks 1924-1967, 3 volumes (Box 6)
  - Shakespeare, Elizabethan drama, and general literature, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Catholicism and Religion (Box 6)
- Manuscripts of writings
  - Scholarly: Jacobean Journal, volumes 1-3
    only volumes 1-2 were published
    - Correspondence 1958-1968 (including, 1968 "history" of the Journal) (Box 7)
    - Typescript Entries
      - 1611 (Box 7)
      - 1612 (Box 7)
      - 1613 (Box 7)
      - 1614 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 7)
    - Notebooks, 4 volumes (Box 7)
  - Fiction (all unpublished)
    - Plays
      - Devil's Bargain (Box 7)
      - Essex (Box 7)
      - The Romantic Lover (Box 7)
      - Uncle Ezra (Box 7)
      - Unrest in Illyria (Box 7)
    - Novels
      - Devil's Bargain (Box 7)
      - Humphrey Maynard, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Illyria: Land of Promise (Box 7)
      - Land of Promise; or Revolution in Illyria (handwritten draft of preceding work) (Box 7)
      - Love's Labours Won (Box 7)
  - Research material, 18 reels
    (including copies of works of Elizabethan literature)
    - Research material (Reel 1)
    - Research material (Reel 2)
      (continued)
    - Research material (Reel 3)
    - Research material (Reel 4)
    - Research material (Reel 5)
    - Research material (Reel 6)
    - Research material (Reel 7)
    - Research material (Reel 8)
    - Research material (Reel 9)
    - Research material (Reel 10)
    - Research material (Reel 11)
    - Research material (Reel 12)
    - Research material (Reel 13)
    - Research material (Reel 14)
    - Research material (Reel 15)
    - Research material (Reel 16)
    - Research material (Reel 17)
    - Research material (Reel 18)